טוב *Tuv*, today's דף *daf* is דף נ' *daf Nun*, 50, and
we pick up at the bottom of מ"ט עמוד ב' *Mem Tet
Amud Bet*, and today's דף *daf* is going to focus on, we
are now—this whole remainder of this פרק *perek* really focuses us on
בור bor *bor*, the one thing that we sort of haven't given
a focused attention to, certainly not in terms of the פסוקים pesukim.
*psukim* in the תורה Torah *Torah*, and the משנה mishnah *mishna* spoke
about digging in one domain and opening in the other with the
point being that a בור bor *bor* is defined by where the
opening is. And the משנה mishnah *mishna* basically says that whether its
opening is in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim. *reshut harabim* or in רשות
היחיד reshut hayachid *reshut hayachid*, חייב chayiv *chayav*. Okay, so it doesn't
matter which one. And now we're going to turn to the גמרא
Gemara's *Gemara* and see that there was a debate. Of course, our
intuition is that a בור ברשות הרבים bor b'reshus harabbim. *bor b'reshut
harabim* should be much more חייב chayiv *chayav* than in רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid, *reshut hayachid* because it's a—it's much more of a public
hazard. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says. תנו רבנן tanu
rabbanan. *Tanu Rabbanan*, about six lines from the bottom on מ"ט עמוד
ב' *Mem Tet Amud Bet*, our rabbis taught: החופר בור ברשות היחיד
bor b'reshut hayachid ופתחו לרשות הרבים l'reshut harabim *hachover bor b'reshut hayachid
u'pitcho l'reshut harabim*, ופתחו *u'pitcho*, I guess it should be, ברשות הרבים
bereshut harabbim ופתחו לרשות היחיד *b'reshut harabim u'pitcho l'reshut hayachid*, question if
you have that גרסא *girsa*, חייב chayiv *chayav*. וזה בור bor האמור
בתורה *V'zeh bor ha'amur batorah*, דברי רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *divrei Rabbi
Ishmael*. So presumably those—what's in the parentheses isn't there as we'll see
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay, so let's take that out. So
you have a בור bor *bor* that's open to רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim *reshut harabim*, you're חייב chayiv *chayav*. This is what רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Ishmael* says, and this is the בור bor *bor*
in the תורה Torah's *Torah*. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר *Rabbi Akiva
omer*, הפקיר hafkeir רשותו ולא הפקיר בורו *hifkir reshuto v'lo hifkir boro*,
זהו בור zehu bor, האמור בתורה *zehu bor ha'amur batorah*. No, if
you actually dig a well in your domain, you own it, and
then you are הפקיר *mifkir*, you renounce ownership over your domain, because
that's necessary because if you own all the area around your well,
you have no liability if somebody falls into it. What are they
doing on your property? But if you give over all the area
around your well to the public and then they have the right
to travel in that space and have access to it and use
it, and you still though own the well, so that's—he says a
בור ברשות היחיד bor b'reshut hayachid *bor b'reshut hayachid* that is a
public hazard, and that's the בור bor *bor* that is written in
the תורה Torah *Torah*. Okay, so what did—so each one says one
of them. One says a בור ברשות הרבים bor b'rshus harabim. *bor
b'reshut harabim*, if you especially take out the parentheses, the other says
a בור bor ברשות היחיד *bor b'reshut hayachid*. Do they hold of
one another? Do they reject one another? Let's see what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. אמר amar, רבה Rabbah, *Amar Rabba*, בבור ברשות
הרבים b'bor b'reshus harabbim. כולי עלמא לא פליגי דחייב *b'bor b'reshut harabim
kuli alma lo peligi d'chayav*. רבה Rabbah, *Rabba*, a man after my
own heart, says, "Look, if it's in the public, give me a
break. Nobody would say you would not be חייב chayiv. *chayav* if
you dig a hole, a pit, right in the middle of the
public domain, public thoroughfare." מאי טעמא mai ta'ama? *Mai ta'ama*, אמר Amar,
קרא *amar kra*, the verse says: כי יפתח ki yiftach, איש בור
bor או כי יכרה ki yichreh איש בור bor *ki yiftach ish
bor o ki yichreh ish bor*. If a man opens up a
well or digs a well. אם על פתיחה חייב chayav על כריה
לא כל שכן *Im al pticha chayav al kriya lo kol sheken*?
If you're liable for opening it, how much more so of course
you're liable for digging it? If the תורה Torah's *Torah* starts with
כי יפתח ki yiftach *ki yiftach*, why does it have to say
כי יכרה ki yichreh *ki yichreh*? אלא ella על עסקי פתיחה ועל
עסקי כריה בעלמא *Ela al askei pticha v'al askei kriya ba'almah*. It
is to tell you that the basis of the liability is because
you have dug it, meaning it is not about ownership. It is
about making the well, making the public hazard, and therefore the question
whether it's in your domain is irrelevant or certainly it's not a
reason to be more חייב chayav *chayav*. The emphasis is you created
a public hazard, and therefore certainly the classic בור bor *bor* in
the תורה Torah *Torah* is doing it is—as a way in which
it's most
hazardous, in
the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim *reshut harabim*. לא נחלקו *Lo nechlaku*, so
everybody would agree with that. So when רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael's *Rabbi
Ishmael* says a בור ברשות הרבים bor b'rshus harabim. *bor b'reshut harabim*
is the בור bor? האמור בתורה *bor ha'amur batorah*, רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* does not disagree with that. Everybody agrees to that.
לא נחלקו אלא ella בבור ברשותו *Lo nechlaku ela b'bor b'reshuto*. The
only question is are you also liable if it's in your domain?
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva סבר *Rabbi Akiva savar*, בור bor ברשותו נמי
חייב chayav *bor b'reshuto nami chayav*, you're also חייב chayav *chayav*, דכתיב
*d'chtiv*, בעל הבור ba'al habor *ba'al habor*, the owner of the בור
bor *bor*, בבור דאית ליה בעל עסקינן *b'bor d'it lei ba'al askinan*.
It's so the תורה Torah. *Torah* is acknowledging that there is a
case where you own it. The presumably the liability is not based
on ownership. Okay, presumably it's still based on the fact that you've
created it, or because you own it you have a responsibility to
cover it up etc. But conceptually it's about having a public hazard.
Okay. ורבי ישמעאל סבר *V'Rabbi Ishmael savar*, no, בעל התקלה *ba'al hatakala*,
בעל הבור ba'al habor. *ba'al habor* does not mean you own it.
It means that you are responsible for it, you created it. But
if you just own it and you did not create it, you
would be פטור patur. *patur*. Okay, now, what is the reason to
be פטור patur *patur* if it's בור bor. ברשותו *bor b'reshuto*? So
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says that the—that the case is, the scenario is
you dug it in the middle of your yard and you were
הפקיר *mifkir* like the משנה mishnah, *mishna* says—you are—or the ברייתא braita
*braita* says—you were הפקיר *mifkir* the area around it. So רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* said there's almost like an implicit stipulation. You can say, "Look
guys, I gave you my property to access, but it was with
the
understanding—not with the sense that it would create liability for me. It
was implicitly with the understanding that I would be פטור patur *patur*
if you fell into my well." You know, because I only—you only
have access to it because I gave you access. So that was
not meant to create any liability. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says that's too
limiting of an explanation because another classic
בור bor. ברשות היחיד *bor b'reshut hayachid* you could imagine— Can you
imagine the case where I dug it in my domain and it's
a hazard and I was not מפקיר mafkir my
רשות? reshus? Meaning, meaning like I just didn't have any שמירה shmira
around it? No, but it's not a hazard if people don't have
access to it. So the example is I dug it right at
the edge of רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim, I dug it right at
my property line. Okay, so it's easy if you're walking in רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim. that you slip and fall into it and that's,
so that would be a case that you'd also have to explain
why they're debating if you're חייב chayav or not or why you
would be פטור. patur. So תוספות Tosafot says the reason you're פטור
patur. is not because you were מפקיר mafkir the area around it
that you can say you implicitly stipulated. The reason you're פטור pattur.
is because you could say, look, this is on my property. It
is your responsibility to not get close to my property. Meaning even
though it's at the edge of רשות הרבים reshus harabbim. and you
could say I have a right to use רשות הרבים, rshus harabim,
you shouldn't make it so close, I could say back to you,
I'm sorry, this is my property line, whether my property line is
because I was מפקיר mafkir the area around it or because I
dug it right at the edge, but nevertheless this בור bor, is
my property and it's your responsibility to keep your distance from my
property. Okay, so it's basically like a שור ברשותי מה בעי. shor
b'reshusi mah ba'ei. What are you doing in my well? That's my
well, you shouldn't be in my well. You have to keep distance
from my well. So therefore that is the reason that רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael's would say you are פטור. pattur Okay, the basic חיוב
chiyuv is creating a public hazard and a public hazard is of
course in the middle of רשות הרבים. rshus harabim On your property,
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael would say you are פטור. pattur Okay, בעל
הבור ba'al habor, just means that you created the hazard. It does
not include a case where you own it that it's on your
property. It's the other person's responsibility to stay distant from my property.
And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, says no, the תורה Torah also includes
that case of owning it. It's that is, it is still a
hazard in that case. And if people are able to get right
up close to it because it's right at the edge, then yes
you are חייב chayav for that case as well. Okay, yes, Rabbi
Dubin? If I'm driving in my car and my car creates a
pothole and you walk by and break your leg,
right, what if I did it בלי כוונה? beli kavana? Well, that's
like the סוגיות sugyos we had before about הפקר, hefker, you know,
הפקיר נזקיו לאחר נפילת אונס hifkir nezikav l'acher nefilas ones or something
like that. So if it was created, if you don't have liability,
negligence in its creation and you also don't own it or whatever,
so there are cases where you're not חייב chayav for having created
it. There has to be some intent or negligence or at least
some ownership of it after the fact that creates a responsibility to
remove it. But that was a whole סוגיא sugya we had earlier.
Is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva disagreeing on רבי ישמעאל's Rabbi Yishmael. case
or is he adding to it? Meaning? He's adding to it. So
that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. So the גמרא's Gemara
going to say like this, אלא מאי זהו בור האמור בתורה דקאמר
רבי עקיבא. ella mai zehu bor ha'amur baTorah d'ka'amar Rabbi Akiva. So
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva agrees that the תורה's Torah. case is that
the case כי יכרה ki yichreh. is that you're חייב chayav? just
for creating it as a, in רשות הרבים. rshus harabim. When he
says זהו zehu, בור, bor that seems very exclusive, like there's only
one type of a בור bor in the תורה torah and it's
the one you own. You're saying that that's not true, that he
agrees to רבי ישמעאל's Rabbi Yishmael, case? So what's the זהו בור
האמור בתורה דקאמר רבי עקיבא? zehu bor ha'amur baTorah d'ka'amar Rabbi Akiva?
זהו בור שפתח בו הכתוב תחילה לתשלומים. zehu bor shepattach bo haksav
techilla l'tashlumim. It means you can't say that the only בור bor
is כי יכרה or כי יפתח, the only בור bor. is a
בור ברשות הרבים. bor bereshut harabim. What about the פסוק pasuk בעל
הבור ישלם? ba'al habor yeshallem? So this is the well that when
you own it, that's the well the תורה's talking about when it
talks about paying, it calls you a בעל הבור. So how can
you ignore that case? So it does not mean these are not
mutually exclusive positions. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael excludes רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, does not exclude רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. Even
though the language is זהו, that's not meant to reject רבי ישמעאל,
Rabbi Yishmael, that's just to say this is also a case of
the בור bor. in the תורה when you own it. Okay, that's
רבא's Rava's way, which starts with the idea that fundamentally the חיוב
chiyuv is based on creating the public hazard. רב יוסף Rav Yosef
אמר, now רב יוסף Rav Yosef goes in the opposite way. רב
יוסף אמר בבור ברשות היחיד כולי עלמא לא פליגי דמחייב. Rav Yosef
amar b'bor b'reshus hayachid kuli alma lo peligi d'michayiv. No, the opposite.
Fundamentally it starts that the חיוב chiyuv is based on owning the
well. Okay, this is more of an idea of ממון המזיק, mamon
hamazzik, right? As opposed to that you could say the other one
was a type of an אדם המזיק adam hamazzik indirectly. You created
a hazard, you therefore brought about somebody's injury. This is a ממון
המזיק. mamon hamazzik. The thing you own, the well, created the hazard.
So since it starts conceptually with an idea of ממון המזיק, mamon
hamazzik, everybody agrees the classic בור bor. is the one that you
own, okay, which is I think counterintuitive but that's what we're saying,
even though it's in your domain. רב יוסף אמר בבור ברשות היחיד
כולי עלמא לא פליגי דמחייב. Rav Yosef amar b'bor b'reshus hayachid kuli
alma lo peligi d'michayiv.
Everybody agrees as long as it's not the middle of your yard,
it's a place where people can get right up next to it.
Okay, מאי טעמא? What's the reason? בעל הבור אמר רחמנא. ba'al habor
amar rachmana. The owner of the well. בבור דאית ליה בעלים עסקינן.
b'bor d'is lei be'alim askinan. So you have an owner. So fundamentally
everybody starts with the idea that the liability of a בור bor
is based on the sense of ownership, okay, and everybody agrees בבור
ברשות היחיד. b'bor b'reshus hayachid. כי פליגי ki peligi בבור ברשות הרבים.
bereshut harabbim,
The debate is when you make it right in the middle of
the street and you don't own it. רבי ישמעאל סבר בבור ברשות
הרבים נמי חייב. Rabbi Yishmael savar b'bor b'reshus harabbim nami chayiv. That's
also חייב. chayav דכתיב כי יפתח וכי יכרה. dechtiv ki yiftach vechi
yichreh. If you open or if you dig. אם על הפתיחה im
al hapesicha I don't get it. If you're חייב chayav for opening,
certainly you're חייב chayav for digging. So אלא שאתיא פתיחה ועיילא כרייה
בעלה ella she'atya p'ticha v'ayla kriya ba'ala to tell you that there's
another liability, a liability not based on ownership, but a liability based
on creating the hazard. And Rabbi Akiva, and Rabbi Akiva would say
back to him, "No, הני מיצריכי צריכי. hanei mitzrichi tzerichi. The Torah
had to tell you both כי יפתח and כי יכרה. It does
not tell you, it's not there to tell you you're חייב chayav
for digging if you don't own it. It's coming to tell you
something else. What is it coming to tell you? דאי כתב רחמנא
כי יפתח, de'i ksiv rachmana ki yiftach, if it had just said
if you open, הוה אמינה פותח הוא דסגי ליה בכיסוי, hava amina
poteach hu d'sagi lei b'chisuy, that if you open it,
it's sufficient to just cover it, right? 'Cause the Torah says ולא
יכסנו. v'lo yechasenu.
The Torah indicates that once you cover it, you're פטור. pattur So
if all you did was open it, all you gotta do is
cover it.
כורה, koreh, if you dig it, לא סגי ליה בכיסוי עד דטמיה,
lo sagi lei b'chisuy ad d'tamyei, I would think covering it is
not enough, you have to refill it. That's a very reasonable thing
to think. So the Torah has to say even though it said
if you open, it has to say if you dig, not to
tell you you're חייב chayav if you dig. Of course you're חייב
chayav if you dig. To tell you that you're פטור patur, if
you covered it, even though you created it and even though there's
still a well underneath your cover.
Okay. So עד דטמיה. ad d'tamyei. So ואי כתב
רחמנא כי יכרה, v'i ksiv rachmana ki yichreh, if it had just
said if you dig, then that's obvious what I would have thought.
הוה אמינה כרייה הוא דבעי כיסוי, hava amina kriya hu d'ba'ei chisuy,
משום דעביד מעשה. mishum d'avid ma'aseh. Sure, digging, there you're liable until
you cover it because you actually created it. אבל פותח דלא עביד
מעשה, aval poteach d'lo avid ma'aseh, if all you did was you
opened a pre-existing well, אימא כיסוי נמי לא בעי, eima chisuy nami
lo ba'ei, maybe you wouldn't have any liability, which would be funny,
but the point is you obviously could not infer liability from opening
from a case of liability from digging. קא משמע לן. ka mashma
lan. Okay. So therefore you needed to say both. That you're liable
even for opening, but you're פטור patur even if all you did
was just cover a well that you actually dug. But it is
not to tell you that the liability is based on creating the
hazard. For Rabbi Akiva, the liability is based on ownership. And therefore,
if you create it in the middle of רשות הרבים, rshus harabim?
huge public hazard, but you don't own it, you're פטור patur according
to Rabbi Akiva. I know it doesn't make sense. This is a
formalism of בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. אלא מהי זהו בור האמור בתורה
כרבי ישמעאל. ella mai zehu bor ha'amur b'Torah k'Rabbi Yishmael. So if
Rabbi Yishmael agrees that you're חייב chayav on a בור bor. that
you own, when he says, "And this is the well that you
are חייב chayav. in the Torah," he doesn't need to exclude a
בור bor. that you own. So what does he mean? He means
no, this is also a case. זהו בור שפתח בו הכתוב תחילה
לנזיקין. zehu bor she'p'tach bo hakatuv t'chila l'nezikin. When the Torah begins,
he's saying to Rabbi Akiva, "How can you say the only well
in the Torah is בעל הבור, one that you own? It says
כי יפתח או כי יכרה." ki yiftach o ki yichreh. So this
idea when you dig it in רשות הרבים rshus harabim, is also
the well that's referred to in the Torah. So זה zeh does
not mean to exclude Rabbi Akiva's case of owning it, but it's
to say you can't say that this isn't the case, one of
the cases in the Torah. One of the cases in the Torah,
when it is talking about digging it, is talking about a בור
ברשות הרבים. bor birshut harabim. Okay, so even though their debate looks
like they completely, it's mutually exclusive. Rabba on the one hand wants
to say everybody agrees to the conceptual base of creating the hazard
in רשות הרבים. rshus harabim, The question is owning it. And Rav
Yosef wants to say the opposite, that everybody agrees to the conceptual
base of owning a
well. And I totally agree with Michael, this is very counter-intuitive. But
the question is, if you dig it without owning it, are you
also going to be חייב? chayav. But that really thinks about בור
bor? as a sense of ממון המזיק. mamon hamazik. And therefore you
have to start with the idea that you own it. Okay. By
the way, I just want to sort of, I don't know if
I should say this, but I will, okay, to complicate a thing
a little bit, is that when, if you take a Rav Yosef
approach that fundamentally it's based on ממון המזיק, mamon hamazik, how do
you understand Rabbi Yishmael that says you're also חייב chayav. when you
dig it in רשות הרבים? rshus harabim. Are there two conceptual ways
of being חייב chayav. for a בור? bor One way is ממון
המזיק, mamon hamazik, one way is more of an אדם המזיק adam
hamazik creating it? Or do you say no, that what Rabbi Yishmael
is saying is if you dug it in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim.
you are considered to be the owner? You might remember a statement
we had a while ago, שני דברים אינם ברשותו של אדם ועשאן
הכתוב כאילו הן ברשותו. shnei devarim einam birshuso shel adam v'asaan hakatuv
k'ilu hen birshuso. Two things you don't own and the Torah made
it as if you own. חמץ בפסח ובור ברשות הרבים. chametz b'Pesach
v'bor b'rshus harabim. Right? So you could say that if you take
a Rav Yosef approach, everybody agrees that it's based on ownership. It's
just that Rabbi Yishmael's only based on ownership, there's no other conceptual
basis. But Rabbi Yishmael says if you create it in רשות הרבים,
reshut harabim the Torah is considering you to be the owner. Okay,
and that's, so that's interesting, right, whether the ones that say both,
are they working with two models, or they're conceptually saying
just
one model? Ownership includes a case of בור bor ברשות הרבים. bereshut
harabbim, Or you could say creating a בור bor includes a case
of a בור bor in your domain that's at the edge of
רשות הרבים. reshut harabim, The fact that it's yours and you have
responsibility is like you created it. Okay. So these are the questions,
two different models of חייב chayav for בור. bor, One is ownership,
one is creating it and making a hazard. Yes, Michael. But again,
everyone would still agree that if the public, let's say the public
domain, you know, they're digging, doing construction projects and they don't cover
it well, and the עירייה iriyah is just חייב chayav. even though
he creates it.
Right? Well, that's... I
mean the question is does it have you know that's a really
interesting question. Let's even say that the public has the right to
do it, right? We've found before that you can have a right
to throw things in ברשות הרבים bereshut harabbim, and you're still חייב
chayav for it. So if the public has the right to go
ahead, you know, the city is empowered by the people of the
city to go ahead like right now they're doing this on my
street. They've been doing it for weeks, tearing up the street. Actually,
as I was walking here they were actually removing a manhole cover
and I was going to take a picture of it because it
was a perfect like בור. bor Anyway,
so would you say, you know, oh well yeah but they're still
חייב chayav and then the person חייב chayav is the person is
the נעבעך, nebach, the poor worker that got assigned the job of
digging it? So I don't know because you know there isn't a
corporate,
presumably they are if the city has the right to do it,
an individual might be have the right to throw the garbage in
the street but still be חייב. chayav I assume if the city
has the right to dig wells, but I don't know, you know,
you can sue New York City, right, if they're irresponsible. Like potholes,
but there is no corporate entity of the city to sue and
I assume that we're not going to be מחייב mechayev the poor
worker who got the job to dig the well.
Regarding potholes, the הלכה halacha is regarding potholes, if it's the months,
the winter months, I think it goes until like April or May,
they're actually פטור, patur, but afterwards they're חייב. chayav. Oh that's just
like the גמרא Gemara about about throwing out your waste during the
summer or the winter. That's interesting. Okay, yes. Is it conceptually what
you have here is an idea that if you make something, you
own it, right? Well no, that's what I said. That's one way
of understanding רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael, that it's conceptually like you own
it. The other is saying that no, he doesn't need a model
of ownership. One model is ownership, the other model is a type
of an אדם המזיק, adam hamazik, if you're a causation, you dug
it, you caused it, you're to blame. So that's the question within
רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael Do you try to just say an expanded
model of ownership or is he working with two models? Yes, liability's
responsibility for the damage. What? Liability's responsibility for the damage. Right. Yes,
I was saying that in הלכה halacha I don't know if there's
דעת הקהל. da'at hakahal. Okay, but my question, I'm sorry, my question
is if you take the ownership model, how could you ever be
מפקיר mafkir, anything? I put an object out there in ברשות הרבים,
bereshut harabbim. I created a בור, bor I'm going to say I'm
מפקיר, but I created a בור bor in ברשות הרבים, bereshut harabbim,
right? I put an object out there, someone can trip over. Yeah.
Okay, so what? I mean what you're saying is what we were
saying before, which is that it's it is very counter-intuitive, but there
is a position according to רב יוסף Rav Yosef according to רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. that you dig a well in ברשות הרבים, bereshut
harabbim. you create this huge public hazard and you're פטור patur because
technically you don't own it, right? Because it's גרמא בנזיקין. grama binizikin.
Right, that's what we've been dealing with all along. Negligence, fault, whatever's
not enough. You need to either do a direct act or operate
through one of the formal categories. So yes, that is the ironic
position of רבי עקיבא according to רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: מיתיבי, Meitive, okay. החופר בור ברשות
הרבים ופתחו לרשות היחיד פטור. Hachofair bor bireshut harabbim upitacho lireshut hayachid
patur.
Okay,
so it's open to רשות היחיד reshut hayachid you're exempt אף על
פי שאין רשאי לעשות כן af al pi she'ein rashai la'asot kein
but even though you were you clearly violated a law here by
digging under the ברשות הרבים. bereshut harabbim, Why? לפי שאין עושים חלל
תחת רשות הרבים, Lefi she'ein osim chalal tachat reshut harabbim, you don't
have any right to dig a cavity under ברשות הרבים, bereshut harabbim
you're asking for trouble: A, it's not your domain, B, somebody could,
you know, crash in through the through the top. Nevertheless, since it's
open to a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid you're exempt. It's not open
in the ברשות הרבים. bereshut harabbim Okay. החופר בורות שיחין ומערות, Hachofair
borot shichin ume'arot, however
if you dig, on the other hand, wells and canals and whatever
other types of wells,
ברשות היחיד ופתחו לרשות הרבים חייב. bireshut hayachid upitacho lireshut harabbim chayav.
You're חייב. chayav. So this ברייתא braita is clear that the חיוב
chiyuv is for ברשות הרבים, birshut harabim right? If you open it
in רשות היחיד reshut hayachid you're exempt, you open it in ברשות
הרבים you're חייב. chayav Okay. והחופר בור ברשות היחיד הסמוכה לרשות הרבים,
Vehachofair bor bireshut hayachid hasmucha lireshut harabbim,
now
if you dug it in your domain right at the edge of
ברשות הרבים כגון אלו החופרים לאושין kegon elu hachofrim l'ushin like those
that dig for creating a foundation for a building, רש"י Rashi, says
these are like the ditches around a building foundation, פטור patur. you're
exempt. רבי יוסי בר יהודה מחייב. Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda mechayev. רבי
יוסי בר יהודה Rabbi Yose bar Yehuda says you're חייב chayav even
though you were creating it for your building foundation and it's all
very nice, that doesn't allow you to do it right at the
edge of your domain עד שיעשה מחיצה עשרה, ad she'ya'aseh mechitzah asarah,
you have to make a
barrier עשרה asarah high to keep people away from it, a fence,
או עד שירחיק ממקום דריסת רגלי אדם מקום דריסת רגלי בהמה ארבעה
טפחים o ad she'yirchak mimmekom d'risat raglei adam mekom d'risat raglei behemah
arba tfachim and some say ארבע אמות arba amot which makes a
little more sense. Or that you have to actually not do it
right up against your property line assuming that the public domain goes
right against your property line, you have to, it's not based on
an invisible property line, you have to separate it ארבעה טפחים arba
tfachim or I think more logically ארבע אמות arba amot like six
feet from the place where people actually walk. Okay, so if people
where you find where that place is that people actually walk and
you have to move it six feet away from there, otherwise you
are creating a hazard. I don't care that you're doing it for
your building foundation. Now, the problem with this ברייתא braita is it
starts by saying a בור bor? that opens in רשות היחיד reshut
hayachid, you're פטור, patur and then it says when you have this
בור bor? in your domain right at the edge so that you're
doing it for your building foundation, you're חייב. chayav So the ברייתא
braita is not consistent. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, המאני, ha-mani, who is it
going like? בשלמא bishlama to רבה, Rabbah it's good according to רבה,
Rabbah, remember רבה Rabbah says everybody starts with the idea that you're
חייב chiyuv in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim So בשלמא bishlama to רבה,
Rabbah, רישא reisha רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael the beginning that says only
רשות הרבים reshut harabim and not רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. is
רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael וסיפא v'seifa רבי עקיבא, and the end that
says you're חייב chayav? even in רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid. that's רבי
עקיבא. I don't know that that's a good resolution. Okay, usually you
don't like splitting a ברייתא braita among two תנאים, tannaim, but at
least it's a resolution. אלא רב יוסף, ela Rav Yosef, but remember
רב יוסף Rav Yosef, says everybody says you're חייב chayav. for רשות
היחיד. reshut hayachid. So the beginning of the ברייתא braita is clearly
against that, because the beginning of the ברייתא braita says you're פטור
patur for רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid, אלא רב יוסף, Rav Yosef בשלמא
סיפא דברי הכל, bishlama seifa divrei hakol, the end is it could
be like everybody because that's speaking about being חייב chayav? in רשות
היחיד. reshut hayachid, אלא רישא, ella reisha, the beginning, מאני, mani, who
is it going like? לא רבי ישמעאל ולא רבי עקיבא, lo Rabbi
Yishmael v'lo Rabbi Akiva, it's not going like anybody because according the
beginning says explicitly if it's in a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid? you're
פטור. patur So אמר לך amar lach רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, רב
יוסף Rav Yosef, would say to you know: כולה דברי הכל, kulah
divrei hakol, it's going like everyone. ורישא v'reisha and the beginning is
an easy case, when it says you opened it in רשות היחיד,
reshut hayachid the question is where in רשות היחיד? reshut hayachid, ורישא
שלא הפקיר לא רשותו ולא בורו, v'reisha shelo hifkir lo reshuto v'lo
boro, the beginning is it's a well that has the opening in
the middle of your yard. You're פטור patur because
not because it's a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. that nobody has the
right to have access to. All right, maybe it is obvious. No,
so the גמרא Gemara, is going to say or רש"י Rashi says,
somebody says, I forget at this stage, that the חדוש chidush is
that even though you dug under the רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, we
don't say that that violation of that law of digging under רשות
הרבים reshut harabim. gives you liability if somebody falls in the well.
They're separate issues. At the end of the day, nobody had a
right to go into your yard and you're not liable just because
somebody could say that the whole well was done illegally, dug illegally.
But you still have to fill it up. Yeah, that's a different
story, but you're not liable for damages. Okay, so he says a
very simple point. The end of the ברייתא braita, is talking that
it's at the edge of רשות הרבים reshut harabim. and that's why
you're חייב. chayav. This is assuming a בור bor? ברשות היחיד you're
חייב. chayav. The beginning that says you're פטור patur is because you
own the area around it, so of course you're exempt, nobody has
a right to get up to your בור. bor Okay.
Okay, אמר רב אסי, amar Rav Assi, השתא דאוקימנא hashta d'okimna now
that you've said the רב יוסף דברי הכל Rav Yosef divrei hakol
that it works for רב יוסף Rav Yosef according to all opinions,
which is a very nice read of the ברייתא, braita. לרבה נמי
לא תוקמה כתנאי, l'Rabbah nami lo tokmah k'tannai, you also don't have
to say it's split between two תנאים tannaim the ברייתא. braita מדירישא
mi-de-reisha רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael the beginning is רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael,
who says you're חייב chayav in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael. according to רבה says you're חייב chayav only in רשות
הרבים. reshut harabim, Okay wait a minute, no, hold on. According to
רבה, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says you're חייב chayav only in רשות
הרבים. reshut harabim. So the beginning says
you're פטור patur in רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid
that's רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, that your חייב chayav is only רשות
הרבים reshut harabim. not רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. So the רישא reisha
is רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. So that would be a case even
רשות היחיד reshut hayachid at the edge of רשות הרבים, reshut harabim
nevertheless you're פטור patur, because it's because רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says
you're פטור patur in
רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid וסיפא נמי v'seifa nami רבי ישמעאל, the end
is also רבי ישמעאל. If that's true, what's the discussion about this
digging of a foundation? Why should you be חייב? chayav רבי ישמעאל
says you're פטור patur in רשות היחיד reshut hayachid even at the
edge of
רשות הרבים. reshut harabim
וטעמא v'taama דלאושין, d'la-ushin, and the problem at the end is that
the end sounds like the only reason the תנא קמא tanna kamma
exempted you was because you were doing it for the sake of
your building foundation. It sounds like fundamentally you're חייב. chayav. Why are
you fundamentally חייב? chayav So the גמרא Gemara says כגון דארח וחבולי
k'gon d'arach v'chabuli לרשות הרבים because you went a little bit overboard,
you didn't keep within your border line,
you actually went over the line into the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim,
Okay, so basically right, if this is your רשות הרבים reshut harabim
and this is your רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, and you're digging a
hole and you're digging your whatever your foundation, if you went just
a tiny bit over even if it's only like one inch over,
nevertheless you've now created a public hazard in רשות הרבים reshut harabim.
and therefore you're going to be חייב. chayav. Okay, so again so
the ברייתא braita basically says like this: The ברייתא braita says רשות
היחיד reshut hayachid. you're going to be פטור, patur, and then the
second part of the ברייתא braita, says if you're doing it לאושין,
l'ushin,
right for your building foundation in רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid. so then
it goes says then it says you're going to be according to
the first approach פטור patur and according to the second approach, I
forget who it was who was the second opinion in the ברייתא,
braita רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yossi
b'Rabbi Yehuda says you're going to be חייב. chayav Okay, but what's
clear is that the reason you're פטור patur is we're giving you
a bit of a pass because you're doing it for the sake
of your building foundation, okay? And that's that's, you know, that's why
you're פטור, patur but fundamentally the stuff here at the end says
you're חייב chayav in רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Okay, so here the
basic point here is that you're חייב chayav in רשות היחיד. reshut
hayachid. So how do you explain the רישא reisha and the סיפא?
seifa? So one explanation is it's basically assumes you are חייב chayav
in רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Okay, that's רב יוסף. Rav Yosef Everybody
agrees that you're חייב chayav in רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Here you're
פטור patur because it's in the middle of your yard, okay? So
this case that you're פטור patur is it's in the middle of
your yard,
and this case that you're חייב chayav. is at the edge of
your yard, okay? It's an exemption for, okay,
and if it's exempt, it's a special exemption for אושין. ushen. That's
how רב ישמעאל, Rabbi Ishmael, that's how רב יוסף Rav Yosef. says
it, but fundamentally you're חייב. chayav. רבא Rava says, רבא Rava says,
no, fundamentally you're פטור patur, in רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid It's רב
ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael who says fundamentally you're פטור patur in רשות היחיד.
reshut hayachid So in this case you're going to be פטור patur.
even over here. So in this case why are you חייב chayav
fundamentally, if it weren't for the exemption of אושין, ushen, because you
went over the line. So it's really not a רשות היחיד reshut
hayachid case, it's really a case that you went over the line.
Okay. But they actually fell in your רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. part,
does it make a difference? Doesn't make a difference. I mean, how
would they get here without first going through there? I mean, I
guess that would be an interesting question, right? I don't know the
answer to that. Let's say, yeah, you're running, or no, or let's
say here it went over the line, but here like part of
it went over the line and they fell on the part that
didn't go over the line. That's an interesting question. I don't know
the answer. Okay. So גמרא Gemara, says like this. Okay,
מיתיבי, meitivei, I'll ask you, החופר בור ברשות היחיד ופתחו לרשות הרבים
חייב. hachofer bor b'reshut hayachid u'petacho l'reshut harabim chayav. Okay, if you
made it in רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. and opened it to רשות
הרבים, reshut harabim, you're חייב. chayav. ברשות היחיד הסמוכה לרשות הרבים, b'reshut
hayachid hasemucha l'reshut harabim, however if you kept it in your domain,
but it was right up at the edge of רשות הרבים reshut
harabim, פטור, patur you're exempt. So this ברייתא braita? is clear that
you're only חייב chayav in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim בשלמא לרבא כולה
רבי ישמעאל. bishlama l'Rava kula Rabbi Ishmael. According to רבא Rava that's
רב ישמעאל. Rabbi Ishmael. רב ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says you're חייב chayav,
only in רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, not in רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid.
אלא רב יוסף, Rav Yosef now רב יוסף Rav Yosef says that
everybody says you're חייב chayav. in רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid So how
do you explain this ברייתא? braita This ברייתא braita. says you're פטור
patur in רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Okay.
בשלמא רישא רבי ישמעאל, bishlama reisha Rabbi Ishmael, the beginning that says
you're חייב chayav, in רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabim. fine, that's רב ישמעאל.
Rabbi Ishmael. אלא סיפא מני? ela seifa mani? But the end is
explicit. The end says it's רשות היחיד reshut hayachid right up at
the edge and you're going to be פטור. patur, Who is that?
רב יוסף Rav Yosef says everybody says you're חייב chayav. for רשות
היחיד. reshut hayachid לא רבי ישמעאל ולא רבי עקיבא. lo Rabbi Ishmael
v'lo Rabbi Akiva. אמר לך, amar lacha, he'll say to you, לאושין
ודברי הכל. l'ushen v'divrei hakol. No, no, no, רב ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael
and רב עקיבא Rabbi Akiva could agree. The reason you're פטור patur.
there is a special exemption, you're doing it for the sake of
your building foundation. So, רב, Rav, now of course that's not פשט
pshat at all in the ברייתא. braita. Why do we care you're
doing it for your building foundation? Whatever, it's sort of like sometimes
we give people a little bit of a little latitude, you know,
because you got to be for the public well-good. On the one
hand you have to be concerned about creating public hazards and on
the other hand people have to be able to build their buildings.
You know, make your building a little smaller? I don't know what
to tell you. Look, you're right, it is funny, especially given that
we've seen that you can like spill your trash in רשות הרבים
reshut ha-rabim. and you have a right to do it but you're
still חייב. chayav. But maybe I don't know, maybe it's a temporary
thing and eventually you're going to fill it once you build your
building. So some whatever it is, there's an assumption that there was
a need to give people a certain latitude. But it's certainly not
פשט pshat in the ברייתא. braita The ברייתא braita says you're פטור
patur. for רשות reshut היחיד and we've turned the ברייתא into a
special case which wasn't even mentioned, a special exemption then what you
were doing it for your building foundation. Okay. So, so anyway there
are clear ברייתות braitot that indicate like it's one way and not
the other way, but the גמרא Gemara has found a way out
of it. Now we continue. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. חפר ופתח ומסר
לרבים. chafar u'patach u'masar l'rabim. If you dug it in your domain
and you opened it up, right, and now you gave it over
as a gift to the to the community, not just the area
around it, the well itself. Here's a well that you can use
to store things in that collects rain water. It's my gift to
the community. Okay, so in that case פטור, patur you're exempt. Okay,
because you because, you know, it was never a hazard. First it
was yours and then it was given over to the community and
so you didn't have any liability what would happen after that point.
חפר ופתח ולא מסר לרבים, chafar u'patach v'lo masar l'rabim, however if
you dug it and opened it and you didn't give it to
the community, חייב. chayav Now that seems to be the position that
a בור ברשות היחיד you're חייב chayav on. Okay, and presumably it
is in some place where it still is close enough to the
public domain that it could be a hazard. So if you held
onto the ownership over it, okay, then then you're going to be
liable. וכן מנהגו של נחוניא חופר בורות שיחין ומערות. v'chen minhago shel
Nachunya chofer borot shichin u'mearot. This was the practice of נחוניא Nachunya
the digger of wells and ditches, שהיה חופר ופותח ומוסר לרבים, shehaya
chofer u'poteach u'moseir l'rabim, he would dig it and open it and
give it over to the and give it over to the masses.
וכששמעו חכמים בדבר, u'chshesham'u chachamim badavar, when they heard about this, אמרו
קיים זה הלכה זו. amru kiyem zeh halakha zu. This one fulfilled
this הלכה. halakha. הלכה זו ותו לא? halakha zu v'tu lo? What
is the only הלכה halakha in his life he ever fulfilled? אלא
אימא אף הלכה זו, ela eima af halakha zu, even this הלכה.
halakha. I got to tell you I don't fully understand... And I
don't understand the word, first of all, פתח. patach. Of course he
פתח. patach. If you're being חופר, chofair, it's already פתוח. patuach. What
do you mean פתח? patach? Like you mean he opened it for
business, you mean he made it into a functional well, not exactly
sure what the function of the word פתח patach is over there.
But anyway,
like okay, anyway, but
the, he's just using the echoing the פסוקים. pesukim פס... yeah, I
mean maybe it means או פתח? Maybe it's חפר או פתח? chafar
o patach? Maybe you're right. Maybe that's the point. Okay, but once
you give it over to the רבים, rabbim, then you're going to
be פטור. patur. You can't say, oh, you dug it, you're still
חייב. chayav Like no, it's now owned by the רבים, rabbim, it's
their responsibility to decide what to do with it. Of course one
wonders let's say the רבים rabbim never asked for it, right? Let's
say you basically dug a well that doesn't serve much of a
purpose, it's a public hazard in your, you know, right at the
edge of רשות הרבים, reshut harabim. and you know what? I'm just
going to give it over to the community. Like I'm not exactly
sure if the community gets to decide whether or not to accept
your gift or not. If he dug it in
רשות היחיד as he says. Yes. Okay.
If you look at רש"י, Rashi רש"י Rashi describes the act of
giving it over to the community. רש"י Rashi... four lines before it
gets wide, ומסר לרבים, umasar larabbim, what he says, דאמר לבני עירו,
de'amar livnei iro, הבור הזה שחפרתי צריך לכם לשתות מהגשמים המתכנסים שם.
habor hazeh shechafarti tzarich lachem lishtot meihageshamim hamitkansim sham. I see that
you need it would be a benefit to you to use this
well because to use where all the rainwater that's collected in here,
וראוי לשתות בהמות מהן, v'raui lishtot behemot meihen, and you can use
it for your animals, הרי הוא מסור לכם. harei hu masur lachem.
I'm donating it to you, to the community. Okay, but I again,
I wonder, let's say it's actually not benefiting the community, can you
just sort of donate it and now it's their responsibility? Okay, what?
Take it back. Take it back. Can you take it back? Does
he have to like הפקיר it? Or is it a... No, I
mean, that's, I mean you're right, it's a good question also like
what is the מעשה ma'aseh still? This is verbal. Do you have
to do a קנין? kinyan? Do you have to do something that
finalizes it? Yeah, it's not clear to me, where is the, right,
where is the other side of this transaction? You know that so,
right, it's a good question. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan: מעשה בבתו של
נחוניא חופר שיחין. ma'aseh bevito shel Nechunya chofair shichin. There was a
story about the daughter, you might have heard this story, about the
daughter of נחוניא Nechunya the digger of
canals, שנפלה לבור גדול, shenafelah l'vor gadol, she fell into a deep
well. באו והודיעו את רבי חנינא בן דוסא. bau vehodiu et Rabbi
Chanina ben Dosa. They called, they came and they told רבי חנינא
בן דוסא Rabbi Chanina ben Dosa about what happened. שעה ראשונה אמר
להם שלום. sha'ah rishonah amar lahem shalom. The first hour he said,
it's fine, it's fine, it'll take care of itself, Solomon will solve
itself. שנייה אמר להם שלום. shniyah amar lahem shalom. The second hour
he said, yeah, yeah, yeah, don't worry, it's all, it'll all be
fine. שלישית אמר להם shlishit amar lahem the third hour he said
to them, עלתה, altah, by now she's out of the well. אמרו
לה, amru lah, so then they went and they found out that
lo and behold she had gotten out of the well. So they
said to her, מי העלך? mi he'elach? How did you get out
of the well? אמרה להם amrah lahem she said to them, you
know it's like those cases you hear right about the miners and
those collapsed mines and they're in there for 40 hours until they're
finally able to get them out of the well. Anyway, this happened
in three hours. How did you get out of the well? אמרה
להם amrah lahem she said to them, זכר של רחלים נזדמן לי,
zechar shel racheilim nizdamen li, I ran into a like a
ram, וזקן אחד מנהיגו, v'zakein echad man'higo, and a certain old person
was leading it. רש"י Rashi says the ram is the ram of
יצחק Yitzchak and the old person is אברהם. Avraham. I'm not exactly
sure what the significance is except that אברהם Avraham and יצחק Yitzchak
maybe they dug wells? Right? I mean one of the main things
that יצחק Yitzchak did was he kept on redigging those wells that
אברהם Avraham dug. Okay, so maybe that's the model of her father
here, you know, נחוניא חופר שיחין, Nechunya chofair shichin, digging wells for
the community. Anyway. What? Like an עקידה? akeidah? Well, it is an
עקידה. akeidah. The idea of the lamb is definitely an עקידה akeidah
thing. But I was trying to think what is the specific עקידה
akeidah relevance? You mean a child here being sacrificed, you know... She's
being saved, like the lamb.
Right. The good deeds of the father is leading to the risk
of the life of the child or something. Oh, that's interesting. Okay,
that's nice. Very nice. Yeah, wells of תורה. What? The wells of
תורה and נחוניא Nechunya is fulfilling the wells of... Oh, because he
was fulfilled... Maybe, seeing well as metaphorical about תורה. I don't see
that as directly here, but maybe. Anyway somehow it doesn't say just
because the old man with the ram came by, it doesn't say
how she magically rose out of the well. I mean was it
magic then she popped out when the guy came by or did
he lower a rope to her? What exactly he did, I don't
know. But anyway, okay but that's what happened. Okay. אמרו לו, amru
lo, so anyway, אמרו לו, amru lo, they said to him to
חנינא Chanina who predicted that she would be saved, נביא אתה? navi
atah? You must be a prophet. אמר להם לא נביא אנכי ולא
בן נביא אנכי. amar lahem lo navi anochi v'lo ben navi anochi.
I'm not a prophet or the son of a prophet, which is
pretty funny because we just were mentioning אברהם, Avraham, you know, so
it's talking about like descent from prophets. Anyway, אלא כך אמרתי. ella
kach amarti. This is what I said to myself. דבר שעסק בו
צדיק מצטער בו. davar she'asak bo tzaddik mitzta'eir bo. This thing that
this righteous person, you know, sort of like devoted his life to,
anguished over, making sure that the community would have wells to drink
from, יכשל בו זרעו? yikasheil bo zar'o? That's to be the stumbling
block for his seed? That should be the reason that his children,
that should be the cause of his child's death? Impossible that God
would allow something like this to occur. That's why רש"י... Rashi says
by the way by the third hour he knew everything was fine,
because by the third hour she would have had to have been
dead had she not been saved. So by the third hour he
knew by this stage she definitely didn't die, so something must have
happened that saved her. Okay. So אמר רבי אחא, Amar Rabbi Acha,
אף על פי כן, af al pi chen, this is a very
fascinating גמרא, Gemara, like the גמרא Gemara could have ended here right
with one of those like nice sense about how God makes everything
work out, השגחה פרטית, hashgacha pratit, like you know the story like
oh God wouldn't let צדיקים tzadikim make a sin, certainly not the
animals of the צדיקים, tzadikim, like the חמור, chamor, or whatever. And
then our sense is like really? Does the world work that way?
Well here the גמרא, Gemara well haha, anyway here the גמרא Gemara,
actually like critiques it right away, this sense of everything's going to
work out. אף על פי כן Af al pi chen says the
גמרא, Gemara where where? אמר אף על פי כן, Amar af al
pi chen, מת בנו בצמא, met bno batzama, his son died out
of thirst. Exactly this irony. He was all about making sure that
everybody would have water and his son died out of thirst. שנאמר
She-ne'emar as the verse says וסביביו נשערה. u-svivav nis-arah. I think נשערה
nis-arah or נשערה? nish-arah? Anyway we're going to read it as נשערה.
nis-arah. Around him is like a very tumultuous מאוד. me'od. מלמד שהקדוש
ברוך הוא מדקדק עם סביביו אפילו כחוט השערה. Melamed she-hakadosh baruch hu
medakdek im svivav afilu ke-chut ha-se'arah. Those that are close to him
even like a hair's breadth. Okay. So God is so exacting. And
therefore on the one hand you say oh it's such a צדיק
tzadik nothing bad will ever happen. Because he's a צדיק tzadik maybe
דווקא davka bad things do happen, because God is very exacting. Of
course here's the whole theology that the way God is exacting to
punish a person is that the child dies, another theology that it's
hard for us to relate to. רבי נחוניא אמר, Rabbi Nechunya amar,
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says, מהכא: me-hacha: אל נערץ בסוד קדושים רבה
ונורא על כל סביביו. El na'aratz be-sod kedoshim raba ve-nora al kol
svivav. God is sort of like in the convocation of the holy
ones he's
mighty and he is awesome of those that surround him. So even
the more closer you are, the סביביו, svivav, the more you are
sort of burned by God's presence or the more God is exacting
is awesome. Now תוספות Tosafot of course now has to reconcile it
because we said two contradictory things. We said דבר שצדיק נצטער בו
davar she-tzadik nitzta'er bo wouldn't happen and now exactly his son died
in thirst. So תוספות Tosafot of course who always have to reconcile
says, דבר שצדיק נצטער בו, davar she-tzadik nitzta'er bo, this is אם
זו מכה היא מינה וביה, im zo maka hi minah u-veih, המת
בנו בצמא. ha-met bno batzama.
So now that we see that his son in the end died
out of thirst, you see that this principle isn't true. So why
was he so certain that the daughter was going to get saved?
ויש לומר Ve-yesh lomar דמכל מקום באותו דבר עצמו לא היה ראוי
להיכשל. de-mikol makom be-oto davar atzmo lo haya ra'ui lehikashel. It
was okay maybe it's one thing that it would be very ironic
that the son would die out of thirst but he wouldn't die
by falling into a well. The well was the actual thing that
the person had actually done. So תוספות Tosafot has to find hair's
breadth difference. תוספות has to find this way of reconciling the two
things. But I think it's still really important whether technically the גמרא
Gemara had that in mind or not that the גמרא Gemara is
like
skeptical. It's refreshing to hear that skepticism here. The world doesn't work
so perfectly. Let me tell you there's a lot of irony and
tragedy in the world and דווקא davka his child died of thirst,
yes. I was thinking maybe one of them talking about the fine
line between the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim, I was thinking about that
too the hair's breadth. You do right up to the edge of
רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabim I was thinking about that too. Okay. אמר
רבי חנינא Amar Rabbi Chanina says רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina כל אומר
הקדוש ברוך הוא וותרן, kol omer ha-kadosh baruch hu vatran,
anybody that says that God is like what's a good translation word
וותרן? vatran? A
foregoes things is like a forgiver isn't the right word, but God
just like
goes, it's the opposite of being מדקדק medakdek and sort of overlook
stuff. Overlooks, yeah. Yeah, whatever, it's fine, doesn't matter, whatever, less than
forgiving. Forgiving, for like a וותרן vatran is like okay fine you
don't give me the exact change I don't mind whatever you let
things go. God lets things go. What? Easygoing. Easygoing yeah but easygoing
has a different connotation. Like lets things go when
a line could be crossed but he lets it go, he's not
מדקדק medakdek and so on. Okay. יותרו חייו. yivatru chayav. So if
that's what you say about God, God will let your be easy
with your life too so you'll suffer the consequences. He won't be
so careful about protecting your life. שנאמר הצור תמים פעלו כי כל
דרכיו משפט. She-ne'emar ha-tzur tamim po'alo ki kol derachav mishpat.
All of his ways are justice. Don't think God forgets things and
forgives things or whatever, everything is going to work out as a
just type of a way. All right? Which is interesting. The same
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina that said that the daughter was saved and
here saying that God is exacting. But you know what it works
well. Maybe what רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina is emphasizing is justice. So
justice means that you're not going to get a pass on some
transgression, but maybe from justice also means that his daughter won't die
by falling into a well. Like justice sort of works both ways.
Okay. This by the way statement, the what is it called, the
מסילת ישרים Mesillat Yesharim
deals with this in his opening and he says I don't understand,
what happened to אל חנון ורחום? El chanun ve-rachum? Hashem Hashem El
Rachum V'Chanun ה׳ ה׳ אל רחום וחנון, Hashem Hashem El Rachum V'Chanun,
God is compassion. How do you say that God does not
forgo things? Forgoing might be the better word here. Doesn't forgo things,
but he's supposed to be compassionate. He says no, the compassion is
that he allows you to do Teshuva תשובה. Teshuva. If you do
Teshuva תשובה, Teshuva, he'll forgive you. But if you haven't done Teshuva
תשובה, Teshuva, he's not going to forgive things that you haven't done
Teshuva תשובה Teshuva for. Okay. Amar Rabbi Chanina, Ve'itayma Rabbi Shmuel bar
Nachmani אמר רבי חנינא ואי תימא רבי שמואל בר נחמני: Amar Rabbi
Chanina, Ve'itayma Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani: Mai dechtiv מאי דכתיב, Mai dechtiv,
what's meant by the verse, Erech Apayim ארך אפים? Erech Apayim? God
is long of face or long to anger, velo ktiv Erech Af
ולא כתיב ארך אף. Velo ktiv Erech Af. Not Apayim אפים Apayim
face. A nose literally is what Af אף Af means by the
way. That's why Af אף Af literally means nose because Charon Af
חרון אף, Charon Af, which is firing anger, is like when the
smoke rises from somebody's nostrils. That's literally the image of Af אף.
Af. The nostrils of a
bull. Right. Anyway, Charon חרון Charon is also like the burning. Anyway,
what does it mean God is long of noses? What is the
plural of Apayim אפים? Apayim? Velo ktiv Charon Af ולא כתיב חרון
אף, Velo ktiv Charon Af, long of anger in the singular. Erech
Apayim latzadikim velarshaim ארך אפים לצדיקים ולרשעים. Erech Apayim latzadikim velarshaim. God
actually takes his time both with tzadikim צדיקים tzadikim and rashaim רשעים.
rashaim. So this is also, I love this Gemara גמרא, gemara immediately
juxtaposing contradictory
statements, almost seemingly contradictory. On the one hand, God is very exacting.
On the other hand, God gives people time. Not only tzadikim צדיקים
tzadikim time, he gives rashaim רשעים rashaim time as well. Okay, so
go figure out how all this works together. Tanu Rabbanan תנו רבנן:
Lo yisakeil adam meirshuto lereshut harabim לא יסקל אדם מרשותו לרשות הרבים.
Lo yisakeil adam meirshuto lereshut harabim. Do not, if you're cleaning out
your yard, throw the stones into the reshut harabim רשות הרבים. reshut
ha-rabim It's a pretty obvious statement, I don't know why you need
the Gemara גמרא gemara to say this. Okay, ma'aseh be'adam echad shehaya
mesakeil meirshuto lereshut harabim מעשה באדם אחד שהיה מסקל מרשותו לרשות הרבים,
Ma'aseh be'adam echad shehaya mesakeil meirshuto lereshut harabim, a certain person was
removing the stones from his yard and throwing them into reshut harabim
רשות הרבים, umatzah chasid echad ומצאו חסיד אחד, umatzah chasid echad, and
a certain chasid חסיד. chasid. Now you might remember that chasid חסיד,
chasid, interestingly in the context of Bava Kamma בבא קמא, Bava Kamma,
has had the meaning of somebody that is very careful about not
causing damage to other people. The Gemara גמרא gemara earlier spoke about
the chasidim harishonim חסידים הראשונים, chasidim harishonim, what they would do to
get rid of their broken glass. They would burn it and bury
it and how careful they were not to accidentally cause damage to
other people while taking care of their own property. So a certain
chasid חסיד chasid found him, amar lo אמר לו amar lo and
said to him, reika ריקא, reika, sort of an empty one, low
life, mipnei ma ata mesakeil meirshut she'eino shelcha lereshut shelcha מפני מה
אתה מסקל מרשות שאינו שלך לרשות שלך? mipnei ma ata mesakeil meirshut
she'eino shelcha lereshut shelcha? Why are you removing stones from a domain
that isn't yours and putting them in the street which is where
you're going to be living? So anyway, he says, ligleig alav לגלג
עליו, ligleig alav,
he mocked him, he said what do you mean? I'm getting rid
of them from my domain and I'm throwing them into the public.
What do I care about the public? I'm cleaning out my domain.
Okay. Liyamim לימים, Liyamim, nitzrach limkor sadeh נצרך למכור שדהו, nitzrach limkor
sadeh, in the end it turned out that he fell into poverty,
he had to sell his yard,
vehaya mehaleich be'oto reshut harabim והיה מהלך באותו רשות הרבים, vehaya mehaleich
be'oto reshut harabim, and he was walking in that domain, venichshal be'otan
avanim ונכשל באותן אבנים, venichshal be'otan avanim, and tripped over the own
stones that he had thrown there. Amar אמר, yafeh amar li oto
chasid יפה אמר לי אותו חסיד, yafeh amar li oto chasid, at
that moment he said what that righteous person said to me was
correct, mipnei ma ata mesakeil meirshut she'eino shelcha lereshut shelcha מפני מה
אתה מסקל מרשות שאינו שלך לרשות שלך? mipnei ma ata mesakeil meirshut
she'eino shelcha lereshut shelcha? You're getting rid of your domain, you're putting
it into a domain that isn't yours, and putting it into a
domain that is mine, because this now has become where I live,
I now live on the
street. So it's obviously a very powerful statement, which is that we
tend to be very guided by self-interest and dismissive of how our
actions might hurt other people or cause injury to other
people, and there's always an interesting question, the people that are less
careful when they're dealing with other people's property and the people that
are more careful when they're dealing with other people's property. So the
natural thing is what do I care? It's injury to other people.
It's not in my domain, as opposed to no this is everybody's
domain and this is adafka אדווקא adafka where you need more care
than what you're doing in what you perceive of as your domain.
In the end of the day that's going to be your domain
and not where you currently are. He's the person who made that
bor
בור. Yeah, which is why the Gemara גמרא gemara is funny. Why
do you have to tell me not to do it? Like of
course you're chayav חייב chayav in this case, it's a bor bereshut
harabim בור ברשות הרבים. Since he made the bor בור. Yeah, oh
he can sue himself you mean. Dachsav min-neiya דכסייה מיניה, Dachsav min-neiya,
he made a bor בור in his own reshut רשות and made
a bor בור. Ah right, it's the exact opposite of Nechunya נחוניה.
Nechunya. It also gets back to the justice aspect, it's like the
justice being punished, by the Nechunya נחוניה Nechunya it was the justice
of his daughter being saved, and here's the justice of him being
punished in the end as a result of his actions. Okay, hachofair
bor bereshut harabim venafal letocho shor o chamor החופר בור ברשות הרבים
ונפל לתוכו שור או חמור. Hachofair bor bereshut harabim venafal letocho shor
o chamor. There you go, that's sort of echoing the pesukim פסוקים
pesukim in the Torah, like we had a similar mishnah משנה mishnah.
that echoed the pesukim פסוקים pesukim by a shor שור, shor, here's
a mishnah משנה mishnah. that echoes the pesukim פסוקים by a bor
בור. An ox or donkey falls in, chayav חייב, chayav you're chayav
חייב. chayav Okay. Venafal sham shor o chamor ba'al habor yishaleim ונפל
שמה שור או חמור בעל הבור ישלם. Venafal sham shor o chamor
ba'al habor yishaleim. Echad hachofair bor, shi'ach, u'mearah אחד החופר בור שיח
ומערה, Echad hachofair bor, shi'ach, u'mearah, whether you are digging a well,
canal, or mearah מערה, mearah, which is also a type of a
well, but it's covered, like a cave is covered, charitzin u'ne'itzin חריצין
ונעיצין, charitzin u'ne'itzin, or other types of ditches, chayav חייב, chayav you're
chayav חייב. chayav Im kein אם כן. Im kein. And למה נאמר
בור? lamah ne'emar bor? Why'd it say בור? מה בור mah bor
it's not limited to only a well, but מה בור mah bor
שיש בו כדי להמית עשרה sheyeish bo k'dei l'hamit asarah the same
way a classic בור is deep, is at least ten טפחים tefachim
deep and has therefore the ability to cause the death of an
animal. אף כל שיש בו כדי להמית עשרה טפחים. af kol sheyeish
bo k'dei l'hamit asarah tefachim. So similarly, you're only going to be
liable if an animal dies if it is ten טפחים tefachim deep
and has that potential to kill, the natural propensity to kill an
animal. And how you're פחות מעשרה טפחים, pachot mi'asarah tefachim, it was
less than this, ונפל לתוכו שור או חמור ומת פטור v'nafal l'tocho
shor o chamor v'met patur then you would be
exempt if an animal died. That is not seen as to be
a natural consequence of a well that's that shallow. ואם הוזק בו
חייב v'im huzak bo chayav but if an animal got damaged you
are going to be חייב. chayav Okay, because it is still able
to cause damage. אמר רב, amar rav, now we have a fascinating
debate of רב rav and שמואל. shmuel. אמר רב בור שחיבה עליו
תורה להבלו ולא לחבטו. amar rav bor shechiiva alav torah l'hevlo v'lo
l'chavato. The בור that the תורה obligated you for, the reason, the
conceptual basis that you're חייב chayav is because of the הבלו, hevlo,
the air in the well, and not the חבטו, chavato, the ground.
There's an understanding that somehow, you know, deep down the air is
I don't know thicker or something like that, that somehow you create
a different sense of a of an I don't even know the
word here, of an air, of a vapor, something of that nature
that's created in the space of the well and that you're חייב
chayav because of that vapor, not because the guy bangs himself on
the floor of the well. Which seems crazy, but the idea is
like it's very hard to imagine that רב rav really believed a
guy falls down, breaks his neck, breaks his leg, or a donkey
does, oh it was the vapor that did it. But it starts
with a problem. It's the problem is that he did not
break
his
leg
on my thing. He broke his leg on the ground which I
don't own if I dug a
בור ברשות הרבים. Okay, now
you could say
you still created
the תקלה. takalah.
Okay,
but
the תקלה takalah I created was what caused him to trip
and to fall.
The thing
that he actually did
the damage was ground, not my ground, it's the public ground. Okay,
so it seems like that seems to have again it's like obviously
it's easy to say look you set up that whole system so
you're liable for what happened, but רב rav seems to feel and
maybe this gets back to this concept of ownership, you need a
more direct connection to the thing that caused the damage. So he
says the air, there's this heavy air that's created that wasn't there
before. The ground was always there, you just exposed ground that was
always there. But what you did create was you created this heavy
air and if that is contributing to the guy's injury then that's
what makes it your injury. So it's not like he's ignoring the
fact that the guy broke his leg because he hit the ground,
okay, but he says what makes that your breaking of the leg
and not the fact that he just hit the, you know, tripped
over the normal ground was the fact that it was your like
הבל hevel was in that בור that was somehow contributing. So the
נפקא מינה nafka mina would be as the גמרא gemara is going
to say, you put a you put something let's say you don't
own it because if you own it maybe it's different, but you
dig a mound ברשות הרבים and a guy trips over the mound
and hits the ground. Okay, so there by the way there it's
easier to understand this principle of קרקע עולם היזיקתו, karka olam hizeikato,
right? It's not you know you hit yourself. Yes, I made you
trip, but the thing that caused the break was the ground, that's
not my ground. So that רב rav would say you're פטור. patur.
There you could actually say I made you trip but I did
not actually hit you. What hit you as it were was the
ground and I'm not connected to the ground. I don't have that
הבל hevel that somehow connects me to the ground and therefore I'm
going to be exempt. So that's what רב rav says. Yes. Dov,
I guess I don't understand. Yeah, you're not the only one. I'm
telling you to interpret it that way. I just took the הבל
hevel always as like חלל, chalal, like I created a חלל, chalal,
like a negative space. In other words, without the חלל chalal you
wouldn't have hit the ground. No, because the גמרא Gemara is going
to say well yes so you're seeing it just as a way
of saying it what makes my חבטו chavato is because I exposed
the ground. But the גמרא Gemara is going to say later that
that there's less הבל hevel in a בור that's less narrow, that's
more wide, that's more open. So clearly it does not see as
just the exposing of the ground. It says like a deep and
a narrow well has a lot of הבל. hevel. A shallow and
a wide well has less הבל. hevel. That's what the גמרא Gemara
is going to say. Is that like the ten טפחים tefachim is
what I understood? No, no, no, it's not no, it's not going
to be about the ten טפחים. tefachim. It's going to be about
like how you'll see, but I hear your point, but I think
it's but yeah, you're dealing with the fact that it's a very
strange idea, so you try to make it a little less strange,
I get it. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, אמר
קסבר חבטו amar kasavar chavato the banging is קרקע עולם הוא דמזיק
ליה. karka olam hu d'mazik lei. That's just ground that you don't
own, you're not directly responsible for that. You needed to have created
the הבל. hevel. And שמואל. shmuel. No, no, no. Yes, you’re חייב
chayav for the הבל, hevel, that is something that you created that
contributed, but you’re certainly חייב chayav. for the banging of the ground.
That’s your fault. You exposed that, and there’s no question that you’re
חייב chayav. for that. Okay, ואם תאמר ve-im tomar לחבטה... le-chavatah... okay,
so ואם תאמר לחבטה אמרת ולא להבלו. ve-im tomar le-chavatah amarta ve-lo
le-hevlo. Maybe somebody should say it’s not the הבל, hevel, if somehow
you have a case that the person didn’t suffer because of an
impact with the ground but he suffered because of the air condition
of the well, maybe you should be fully פטור patur. in that
case. התורה העידה על הבור, Ha-Torah heidah al ha-bor, no, the Torah
said you’re חייב chayav on a בור, ואפילו מלא ספוגין של צמר.
ve-afilu malei s'pugin shel tzemer. The Torah says you’re חייב chayav and
it doesn’t say what type of a בור it is. It could
be filled with, like, pillows, you know, with like nice cushions of
wool, and the Torah says you could be חייב chayav in a
בור if there’s no impact. So clearly everyone assumes that you’re חייב
chayav. even if there’s no impact, there is something that can create
injury without it being about physical impact, and that’s הבל. hevel. And
the question of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel is: are you also
חייב chayav. for חבטה chavatah without הבל? hevel? Okay, so let’s take
a look. By the way, דוב, Dov, that’s already a proof against
you, which is it says הבל hevel can create damage without חבטה.
chavatah. Okay, מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? So what would be a case?
So רש"י immediately says: a broken leg as you would say is
a איכא בינייהו, ika beinaihu, right? It’s not out of, you know,
it’s not from a breathing problem, it’s a broken leg, clearly that’s
חבטה. chavatah. But רש"י says no, if you have הבל, hevel, then
you’re חייב for חבטה. chavatah. Okay, so in a way, the הבל
hevel for רב Rav is a way to get you responsible for
the ground. Okay, so what is a נפקא מינה? nafka mina? איכא
בינייהו דעבד גובה ברשות הרבים. ika beinaihu de-avid govah bi-reshut ha-rabim. You
made a little mound in רשות הרבים and you tripped on the
ground and you hit yourself on the mound and you hit yourself
on the ground. לרב הגובה לא מחייב, Le-Rav ha-govah lo mechayev, for
רב Rav you’re not חייב for that. לשמואל הגובה נמי מחייב, Le-Shmuel
ha-govah nami mechayev, you are חייב. Okay, so that’s a clear case
where the injury was the ground which you don’t have a direct
connection to, you just caused the tripping. All right, so מאי טעמא
דרב? mai ta’ama de-Rav? What’s the reason of רב? Rav? Now by
the way, if you trip on the mound and hit yourself on
the mound, then רב Rav would probably agree you’re חייב. It’s your
mound. Okay, you created the mound. You didn’t just expose a ground,
you created a thing. But if you trip on the mound and
hit yourself on the ground, on the flat ground that was always
there, that’s where רב Rav would say that’s קרקע עולם הזיקתו, karka
olam heizikato, you’re not responsible for that. מאי טעמא דרב? mai ta’ama
de-Rav? What’s the reason of רב? Rav? אמר לך רב אמר קרא,
amar lach Rav amar kra, the verse says ונפל, ve-nafal, and you
fell. עד שיפול דרך נפילה. ad she-yipol derech nefilah. You fell the
normal way, which is face first. Which means somehow if you fell
backwards, you’d be פטור. patur Why? Because when you’re falling face first,
the air sort of, you know, in the well sort of, you
know, hits your face. Right? So you’re sucking in the הבל. hevel.
But if you fall backwards and your mouth and nose are exposed
out, then you’re not sucking in the הבל. hevel. So then you
would be פטור. Okay, go figure. ולשמואל, U-le-Shmuel, and שמואל Shmuel says
no. ונפל כל דהו משמע. Ve-nafal kol dehu mashma. ונפל Ve-nafal means
however you fall in. Okay, תנא, Tanna, let’s just read this. אם
כן למה נאמר בור מה בור שיש בו כדי להמית עשרה טפחים
אף כל שיש בו כדי להמית עשרה טפחים. Im ken lamah neemar
bor mah bor she-yesh bo kedei le-hamit asarah tefachim af kol she-yesh
bo kedei le-hamit asarah tefachim. המשנה Ha-mishnah says the בור is to
tell you that you’re only חייב for a death if it’s ten
טפחים tefachim deep. בשלמא לשמואל אף כל, Bishlama le-Shmuel af kol, what’s
it anything, even beyond a בור? What’s that coming to include? לאתויי
גובה, le-atuyei govah, even to include if it’s a mound. אלא לרב
אף כל לאתויי מאי? Ella le-Rav af kol le-atuyei mai? What’s אף
כל af kol coming to include when it says not only a
בור? So the גמרא says לאתויי le-atuyei what’s mentioned in the משנה,
mishnah. חריצין ונעיצין, charitzin u-ne’itzin, they’re like the ditches. חריצין ונעיצין בהדיא
קתני להו, Charitzin u-ne’itzin be-hedya katani lehu, that’s in the משנה. אף
כל פשיטא לן דאתי לאתויי טפי, Af kol peshita lan de-ati le-atuyei
t’fei, אף כל af kol is presumed to say more than is
in the משנה. So the גמרא says no, תני והדר מפרש, tani
ve-hadar mefaresh, it’s telling you the principle and then it’s spelling it
out. What is included beyond a בור? Other types of ditches and
wells, but if it’s just a mound you’re פטור. Now again the
funny thing is you could have said, because remember רב Rav also
has a case about אבנו סכינו ומשאו שהניחן ברשות הרבים. avno sakino
u-masa’o she-henichan bi-reshut ha-rabim. Everybody remember the stone and the knife in
רשות הרבים that you’re also חייב for. So it is funny, the
גמרא could have said you’re חייב for other things like a mound
or a backpack or a knife if the person gets injured on
the thing itself. Right? רב Rav is only saying, just to be
clear, you’re פטור if you trip over a mound and hit yourself
on the ground, but if you hit yourself on the thing itself,
you’re חייב. So we could have said that that’s also what’s being
referred to in the משנה. Okay, now the גמרא just says, let’s
just read this. והני כולהו למה לי? ve-hanei kulehu lamah li? Why
did you need to tell me all of these different types of
wells? צריכא, Tzericha, you need it. דאי תנא בור, De-ee tana bor,
had it just said a well, הוי אמינא בור עשרה הוא דאית
ביה הבלא. hava amina bor asarah hu de-it beih havla. Yes, a
בור ten טפחים tefachim wide which is narrow and round, that has
a lot of, like, you know, compressed air or whatever the word...
you know, thick air, הוא דאית ביה הבלא. hu de-it beih havla.
משום דקטין וקריך, mishum de-katin ve-karich, it’s... it’s narrow and it’s deep
and it’s circular, excuse me. אבל שיח דאריך, Aval shiach de-arich, but...
but a... a canal or whatever, a ditch that’s sort of long,
it’s not narrow, אימא בעשרה לית ביה הבלא, eima be-asarah leit beih
havla, maybe even if it’s ten טפחים tefachim deep because it’s more,
it’s you know, more... it’s not as narrow, with the same depth
you’re not going to get that same type of a heavy air.
דאי תנא... De-ee tana... Yes, a שיח shiyach עשרה asara does, משום
דקטין. mishum de-katin. It might be wide at one edge, but presumably
it's narrow at the other edge, right? It's like a rectangle. אבל
מערה דמרבעא, aval me'ara de-marba'a, but a מערה me'ara which is a
square and it's wide at both in both directions, אימא בעשרה לית
ביה הבלא, eima be-asara leit bei havla, maybe ten is not deep
enough to create הבלא. havla. ואי תנא מערה איצטריך דמערה הוה אמינא
מערה בעשרה הוא דאית ביה הבלא. ve-i tana me'ara itztrich de-me'ara hava
amina me'ara be-asara hu de-it bei havla. Fine, a מערה me'ara does
have it in ten, משום דמטלא, mishum de-metala, maybe because it's the
top is covered over, so therefore that creates this heavy air. אבל
חריצין, aval charitzin, and a canal, דלא מטלא, de-la metala, that is
not covered over and is wide in both directions, אימא בעשרה לית
ביה הבלא, eima be-asara leit bei havla, maybe it does not have
הבלא havla ten deep. ואי תנא חריצין איצטריך דחריצין הוה אמינא חריצין
עשרה הוא דאית ביה הבלא ve-i tana charitzin itztrich de-charitzin hava amina
charitzin asara hu de-it bei havla משום דלית ביה רויחא מעילויא טפי
מתתאי. mishum de-leit bei revicha me-ilaya tefei mi-tata'ei. The reason that has
הבלא havla is because it's not wider at the top than it
is at the bottom, it's like straight down. אבל נעיצין, aval ne'itzin,
a נעיץ ne'itz which is a type of a ditch, דרויחא מעילויא
טפי מתתאי de-revicha me-ilaya tefei mi-tata'ei is sort of like a funnel,
is wider at the top and narrower below, so אימא בעשרה לית
ביה הבלא, eima be-asara leit bei havla, maybe that doesn't have הבלא.
havla. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that all these things have
הבלא. havla. Okay, so it's clear that הבלא havla is not just
the exposed ground. הבלא havla is some sense of a thicker air
in the well, but clearly like as רש״י Rashi says nobody thinks
that that thing is really causing your leg to break. But you
need that to be to make it more yours and connect you
to the damage that is being done by the banging of the
ground. And if you tripped over a mound and hit yourself on
the mound, you'd also be חייב. The real debate of רב Rav
and שמואל Shmuel is tripping over a mound and hitting yourself on
the flat ground. Is that seen as your damage or is that
seen as the damage of קרקע עולם? karka olam? Okay, we will
end here.